good evening hi my name is sarah i'm from the 400 block of west frederick and like many people here i'm here to address the data center issue i spoke at the planning commission last week and mentioned that i hold a master's degree in international relations with an emphasis in sustainable development so i've studied extensively the importance of resource management and the impact this kind of digital infrastructure has on communities specifically where resources are already strained like in Lancaster the issue with the issues with the data center are many and community members have spoken to the city council about these harms and will continue tonight noise air and water pollution increases in utility costs being held politically hostage by a massive corporation the fact that core weave is a deeply unprofitable company with many billions of dollars in debt and i'm sure that more people tonight will enumerate these many harms i'll reiterate what i think is the most concerning issue which is the enormous strain on our grid on the low end with conservative estimates this data center would use quadruple the amount of energy of all the houses in lancaster city combined and i could talk about these harms extensively but i would like to focus on the next steps that we're looking for as a community last week i spoke to the planning commission among many other concerned citizens and the planning commission acted immediately with some concrete steps and while there's still a lot more we're looking to see from the planning commission they scheduled a public hearing for october 1st and engaged seriously with the possibility of a new zoning category we're here to ask for the same kind of concrete actions from our city council because it has been almost a month since this announcement was made and for the planning commission they made steps within the meeting that we came to them here are just a few examples of the type of concrete actions i'm referring to number one you could earmark the revenue from the building permits for affordable housing the eight million dollars that you've received someone mentioned at the planning commission meeting that it is easier to get an energy guzzling million square foot data center in lancaster than it is to get affordable housing if this project is inevitable use the permit revenue for the city's greatest need two another example you could put pressure on coreweave to new to use renewable energy there There are some data centers in the world that attempt to center their mission holistically around renewable energy. CoreWeave is not one of these. Their data centers in Europe use almost 100% renewable energy, but in the States, many of their data centers don't at all. So why are we not putting this pressure on them? We know they're capable of it. I'm running out of time, so I just want to reemphasize that I'm not here to spit vitriol at you. I actually do believe that many of you really, really care about this community and are working on this. here in a spirit of collaboration to share what we believe would be a specific and tangible next step from you we're really looking for action thank you thank you mr harris our next speaker
please next speaker is nathan bishop good evening good evening my name is nathan bishop i'm a resident of the 100 block of president ave in lancaster township and i'm a renewable energy transactions attorney i'm addressing you today regarding the proposed coreweave data centers out of concern for their impact on the people and environment of lancaster these data centers will bring enormous monetary and environmental costs right now the data center plan for 216 greenfield Road will be equipped with 72 diesel backup generators. Our air quality is already the 22nd in the nation for short-term particle pollution. We need to make our air cleaner, not more polluted. Along with the new diesel generation, the power consumption of the 100 megawatt facility will be drawing from Lancaster's existing power supplies, which are composed of 33% coal-based generation, leading to a huge increase in greenhouse gas emissions. The monetary costs of data centers are already well documented. Rate payers, normal people, end up paying higher electricity prices when new data centers draw upon existing transmission and generation resources. I call the council's attention to two reports on this matter. The report titled Extracting Profits from the Public, How Utility Rate Payers are Paying for Big Tech's Power by Eliza Martin and Ari Pesco of the Harvard Law School Environmental and energy law program and the analysis of the 2025 26 rpm based residual auction prepared by the independent market manager for pjm which is the regional transmission organization servicing lancaster this report demonstrates that normal people are paying billions of dollars in higher electricity bills as a direct result of new data centers and that these costs are only expected to get worse i call upon the city to reject any further data sector applications and with respect to the center plan for 216 greenfield road to coordinate with the state public utility commission and pjm to gain access to all agreements between pjm and core weave to insist on new direct co-located solar plus storage generation paid for by core weave to service all of the electricity and backup power needs of the facility which would help bring green jobs to lancaster prevent air and climate pollution and prevent utility rate hikes and to establish proactive restrictions on the facility from switching to water cooling systems and to address the annoying concern issues thank you for your time and attention to this matter
i'm on the 800 block of third street i was here last week for the planning commission meeting and spoke about some similar things and i heard a lot of people who were numbers people and who who are facts people and I talked about how I'm a feelings person that's what I have to give and as a feelings person there's a lot of big scary stuff that's going on in the world right now and I often find myself wondering what I can do and the only thing that I come up with is that we should all be wailing in the streets right now that's the thing that makes the most sense to me but nobody else is doing that yet so instead I make art and I hang out with kids and right now I'm hanging out with some kids who are four to eight years old and we're building a world we're building an art installation where we're looking at different perspectives we've got a town and a mountain and some water in the underground and when we're building this world we talk about our roles and we talk about the impact of our actions and how what we do in the town affects the mountain and how what happens on the mountain affects the salmon that we put into our river and there's different kinds of people right there's number people and there's feelings people and there's kids and there's power people and right now it seems to me that you guys are the power people and the power people need to take some ideas from these kids who come up with these incredible ideas they have all of these out of the box solutions because they're not bound by silly rules and ideas of like well somebody said that there was an ordinance that we have to do xyz and there's a law about the ha ha ha ha ha ha there's people in power who can change that stuff and come up with innovative ideas and new ideas just like the kids can decide that they don't want a data center in our town because what's going to happen to the animals that live on the mountain and how are we going to breathe and how are we going to drink the water and how are the duck's going to stay upright on the pond that we built when none of us can breathe we're going to have a public health crisis on our hands and i hear a lot of people talking about um boosting the power grid because it's going to take all of this power and such and such and such and what i wonder is what actions can be taken to boost the public health system in lancaster city to deal with the effects that's going to happen when the chronically ill people and the people with asthma and the people with migraines and the people who are on inhalers can't breathe and what's going to happen when our kids can't breathe the kids can't eat the dollars they can't breathe the dollars they can't drink the dollars they don't give a shit about the dollars they just want to breathe and so at that time maybe like is that what happens is that we don't do anything now and then the kids can't breathe and then we're all wailing in the streets because it's all that we have left and all we can do is just be feelings people crying in the streets what are you going do so we don't get to that place what's going to happen how do we keep from getting there thank you
our next speaker mr harris is dan weigel good evening uh dan weigel uh clarendon drive um as you may have noticed there's a petition going around um there's a petition going around in our community about the data center we have hundreds of signatures on it it's been in the news obviously this is a big deal to our community I'd like to take my time tonight first to read the petition to you all as AI companies to send on Pennsylvania to build data centers local governments need to make a choice stand up to big tech or sell out their constituents in Lancaster City we're facing the construction of two AI data centers that have gone under the radar until recently setting aside the negative effects of the global AI race these data centers will cause price hikes for utilities lower the supply of water and electricity and create harmful new air and noise pollution across the country many communities that have become sites for data centers have been forced to deal with rolling blackouts and low water pressure or watching their utility bills become more and more expensive we don't want that to happen in Lancaster City we call on Lancaster City government to do the following one City Council must request from the Planning Commission an ordinance that covers the zoning of data centers and rescind the zoning officers decision to
and storage they are not warehouses to mayor Sirachi and City Council must work with the public to pass a plan that insulates Lancaster residents from the negative effects of data centers for example price hikes for utilities low water pressure and rolling blackouts three city government must act with complete transparency and not issue any further permits to data centers until these changes have been made finally we call on Lancaster City to be a leader in Pennsylvania and stand up for working people like you all over the interests of big tech companies now I'd like to pull the room of those in the room tonight many of you i believe have signed the petition for those who have not who have heard of it for the first time i'd like a show of hands how many of you are with us in our demands and
to you sitting up front i turn the question on you do you hear us and are you with us please raise your hands a bit higher please everyone on city council mayor sirachi do you hear us
and members of the city government thank you i look forward to your actions counselor craig
Thank you all for being here, especially our council and mayor, and for all your service to our community. We appreciate everything you do and for being here. I also appreciate my fellow community members. p.s i'm in the 200 block of north pine street and i own a business here in lancaster city 100 block of chestnut so i uh respect what everyone is having to say here and appreciate all the amazing data what i have a specific question on is that the city of lancaster voted last november to be part of home rule which was most most uh was pushed forward and and discussed and paid for to discuss how that was going to be implemented with the city did vote yes to it i'm writing what i haven't seen anything updated on the city of lancaster website as to how we as citizens can implement our right to petition ordinances i'm not even sure if this was an ordinance passed but i'm looking at article 7 ordinances which says general proposals increases requirements for public notice prior to adoption and article 11 adds citizen ability to petition to propose reconsider or appeal an ordinance by referendum I'd like to know how our council members and our governance here are actually if this is an ordinance that was passed why the public wasn't allowed the petitioning that was guaranteed by us passing home rule which again I haven't seen any updates since all the things have been put on the website as to how our people can use our government that we passed to actually be a participant in these situations which do affect every single person who lives and works in this city and i leave all these wonderful people who have done amazing research to give all the details but that's something i specifically want addressed to our community and you know we had letters coming out saying yes please vote for home rule here's what it's going to do for us now how can we as people who have milked hundreds here have been coming to these events and represent only a portion but how do we get the word out to the rest of our community how they can be involved as well in the governing of our city
500 block of west james street and i'm here to talk about you guessed it the ai data centers so as a resident of lancaster city i fear for our access to water and electricity if this data center is built we already have so much evidence of ai data centers causing droughts such as in Texas where all their data centers combined are projected to use 50 billion gallons of water this year. Residents who are trying to just drink water, shower, and water their plants are being told to conserve their water for the sake of these data centers. Doesn't this sound reminiscent of every other environmental disaster caused by huge corporations? Somehow the solution is always that we need to take shorter showers. Air cooling has been touted as a solution to water shortages However, this is not an option because CoreWeave proudly states on their website that liquid cooling is essential for large-scale AI performance. There are other ways regular citizens will have to pay to accommodate AI. My friend in Illinois now pays $200 a month for electricity in his one-bedroom apartment. His boss pays $600 per month for his house because their electric company, ComEd, passes the cost of electricity to all of its customers to keep up with demand created by AI data centers. for comparison my electric bill in lancaster for a one bedroom has been 30 to 40 dollars per month since 2022 and so was his in chicago the ceo of core weave claims the lancaster data center will drive economic growth but for who himself and his shareholders not the single parent trying to make sure their children have water to drink and bathe not the 20 something year old server working doubles to barely afford their one red bedroom apartment and not the first time home buyer getting ready to pay more bills than they ever have in their life i don't care that you made a silly picture of your dog seemingly out of nowhere i don't care that you think chat gbt is a substitute for a therapist and i don't care that ai wrote your essay so you can graduate and not have to think about these things that you were supposed to be learning i speak for all lancaster county residents when i say we will be paying for these ai data centers with our quality of life and wallets if we do not stop it thank you thank you mr harris our next speaker please next speaker is
reagan layman good evening um my name is reagan layman and i live on the 500 block of north shippen street and i appreciate the council giving us an opportunity today to speak on the issues that are pressing our city since the last city council meeting i noticed that the city has published an faq on ai data centers on their website and while my three minutes doesn't allow me to address each point i'd like to address some of the statements on the web page in response to this data impacts on air quality i understand that the pa department environmental protection is reviewing the permit on backup diesel generators for these ai data centers however this doesn't address the larger picture that the fact that we're seeing across the nation we're restarting coal plants in order to fuel these ai generate ai data centers not to mention we're now seeing through mile island is being restarted to power a microsoft ai data center as well so in the end we're impacting the air quality of not just lancaster but of all pennsylvanians additionally are we supposed to simply trust that these diesel generators will only be run as backup power are we going to have to depend on self-reporting from these ai data centers how are we going to enforce that these permits are being followed and won't change in the future secondly when it comes to noise pollution we're developing on the developer to self-assess the noise impact of course if they're self-reporting i would assume that they're motivated to report as neutral they want to finish this project they want to make money You also state that the city will be reviewing the study. But given that this administration seems to be already biased towards these data centers, this whole FAQ page seems very pro-data center, I have a difficult time trusting that assessment. Once again, I ask, what are the means of enforcement if these AI data centers end up contributing to noise pollution? These companies don't care about us. They only care about profit. Most fines are a slap on the wrist to a billion-dollar company. Will we be tied up in endless litigation if we pursue legal recourse? while i understand that the mayor is pursuing a community benefits agreement with the data centers my understanding is that municipal zoning ordinances are easier to enforce than cbas so why wouldn't we start setting these protections these zoning protections in place now during a time when our clean air and water protections are being stripped away at the federal level we can't afford any complacency on the state and municipal level if we're going to protect our neighbors despite the public turnout i've seen at two different meetings so far despite the thousands of emails that I know that you have received. When I checked the agenda earlier today, I didn't see anything about the data centers, and I'm really disappointed. I'm asking that the council today to amend the agenda to take action and start this rezoning process. Data centers are not warehouses. They should have never been categorized as warehouses and skipped a planning commission meeting. Let's take steps now to protect our communities before it's too late. Thank you, I yield my time.
thank you council president the public works committee did meet we had one agenda item resolution 54 which is authorizing an agreement with the lancaster county conservation district which appears later on our agenda this evening that concludes the public works report of the
you council president the economic development committee did not meet thank you finance committee
councillor arroyo thank you council president the finance committee meeting did or i'm sorry the finance committee did meet we had one item on the on the agenda we heard from director of administrative services tina campbell yesterday for the 2025 mid-year budget report overall the city's finances are on pace as budgeted budgeted revenue is slightly ahead and budgeted expenses are below where they are expected to be at this point this is mostly due to current staff vacancies which are temporary and are looking to be filled this year that concludes my uh report and uh for
committee met last evening august 11 and reviewed the appointments to the downtown investment district already and a board of plumbing examiners and the committee also reviewed re-appointments to the sign commission public art advisory board higher education authority and the board of plumbing examiners i complete my report thank you very much councillor cleeks
MADAM PRESIDENT, I MAKE A MOTION TO APPOINT KATIE SCHIFFLET TO THE DOWNTOWN INVESTMENT DISTRICT AUTHORITY FOR A TERM FROM AUGUST 12, 2025 TO DECEMBER 31, 2029. MASON SAUDER TO THE BOARD OF PLUMBING EXAMINERS FOR A TERM FROM SEPTEMBER 12, 2025 TO SEPTEMBER 12 2026 and we appoint molly kirkhoff to the sign commission for a term from august 31st to 2025 to august 31st 2028 see sava hong binton barry corn hoser and rachel fennig hills to the public are the advisory board for the term for terms from july 31st 2025 to july 31st to 2027. jean wigglers to the higher education authority for a term from january 1st 2025 to january 1st 2030 and eric weiss barry solder sean way and trent myers to the board of plumbing examiners for terms from september 12 2025 to september 12 2026. motion to approve second we have a motion
i missed you when i looked that way no worries thank you council president just wanted to make a comment i'm also very excited about this project i had a chance to partake on the hike maybe a few weeks ago a month ago and was very excited for someone who grew up in the southeast i'd never step foot on parts of that uh area to and there were it was very hard to believe that was in the middle of lancaster city especially uh um and where we were so it's very exciting to see what that's going to be for future generations so very excited about this thank you any additional council
thank you council president this resolution authorizes a routine update to our memorandum of understanding with the lancaster county conservation district the changes being made are primarily administrative in nature including minor word changes uh and allowing lccd to provide documents online and on its website kind of coming into the first 21st century there and decreases plan review and permitting timelines for applications for erosion and sediment control programs from 10 calendar days to five calendar days as well as an update to the lccd to reduce its inspection and inspection response timelines from 10 calendar days to eight calendar days there are no changes to the municipal responsibilities within the mou so it does not change our responsibilities in any way again this is mostly an administrative update to our memorandum of understanding with lccd thank you very much council hirsch counselors we heard
block of east lemon street and um i just want to say that we live in a great community i love that we're getting that environmental thing that's amazing right at the same time we're getting a
and we're destroying the environment at the same time. The priorities aren't there for me. I don't see it. And Mayor Sirachi, I want to address you directly here because you say you can't do anything, right? But as Frank pointed out, you were super, super excited about this building. So why didn't you do anything then? Why have we not tried to do, you have plenty of ideas here that you were given, right? And I understand that we're held back by red tape. And I don't think that a data center truly an awful thing for the community if done right but the thing is this was done with no public input because it was labeled as a warehouse and I'm just struggling to try to figure out where we go from here in terms of you know making sure that this doesn't happen again right and I know you guys say that you're doing your reports and I can't wait to hear them right I'll look at them and you know I will reassess my position then but I understand that the big bad bill is probably going to hurt LDH we're gonna get hurt right and we need to bring new industry to Lancaster I 100% agree with that I just don't think that this is the way to do it we're rushing into it we're just we see it as dollar signs but when in reality it's not gonna bring the jobs that you think it's gonna bring we need technology I truly believe that the tech industry is a major industry that we can have here right a data center sucks I'm just gonna put it right out there data centers destroy their communities right and we talked about potentially gentrifying a community, which I hope we don't, right, and we talked about that. But then we also talked about potentially destroying black and brown communities with data centers. So where do they go? You're gonna kick them out and then you're gonna destroy where they're gonna end up going. I just, I'm struggling to see the connect here, guys.
good evening my name is Abby Haney I live on the 600 block of East Madison Street I didn't come here planning to speak I just wanted to listen I know I've been here talking about the data centers before and we had so many great people who showed up today to continue to advocate for action and so I really appreciate all of you who came I just had maybe one or two things that I'm still kind of wondering from the last time that I was here one of them was the community benefit agreement that I believe was mentioned that would be that'd be figured out between the city and Chris a core we I just have questions again about who is the one who's going to do the negotiating around that is it unilaterally is the community going to be involved with that because i think we really should have the ability to have a say um i also really i don't know if he's here but i also really appreciate dan weigel who came and he had a whole list of things that i believe lancaster stands up had drafted in a letter petition and i really think that those are great actionable concrete steps that the council can take full disclosure i'm here with lancaster dsa and i really appreciate the work that lancaster stands up is doing in partnership with us so i really really hope that you guys will take everything that's been said today take it in and really think about what the next steps are going to be because it's clear to me that the community doesn't want this so we'd really like for you to have some action thank you thank you are there any additional speakers for
councilor ahmed thank you council president and i do want to thank all of the members of the community who have come out and spoken at the past several meetings i did request a report on the current status of the data center and what council's options are moving forward and i do look forward to that report thank you that concludes my comments thank you very much